Language modeling is one of
the most basic and
important task
in natural language processing.
It is also one that
RNNs do very well.
In this video, you'll
learn about how to
build a language
model using an RNN,
and this will lead up toward
a fun programming exercise
at the end of this week,
where you build a language
model and use it to
generate Shakespeare like texts
and other types of texts.
Let's get started.
What is a language model?
Let's say you're building a
speech recognition system
and you hear the sentence,
the apple and pear
salad was delicious.
What did you just hear me say?
Did I say the apple
and pair salad?
Or did I say the
apple and pear salad?
You probably think
the second sentence
is much more likely.
In fact, that's
what a good speech
recognition system would output,
even though these two sentences
sound exactly the same.
The way a speech
recognition system
picks the second
sentence is by using
a language model which
tells it what is
the probability of either
of these two sentences.
For example, a language model
might say that the chance of
the first sentences is 3.2
by 10 to the negative 13,
and the chance of the
second sentence is say
5.7 by 10 to the negative 10,
and so with these probabilities,
the second sentence is
much more likely by over
a factor of 10^3 compared
to the first sentence,
and that's why a speech
recognition system
will pick the second choice.
What a language model does is,
given any sentence,
its job is to tell you what is
the probability of that
particular sentence,
and by probability
of sentence, I mean,
if you were to pick up
a random newspaper,
open a random email,
or pick a random webpage,
or listen to the next
thing someone says,
the friend of you says,
what is the chance
that the next sentence
you read somewhere out there in
the world will be
a particular sentence like
the apple and pear salad?
This is a fundamental
component for
both speech recognition
systems as you've just seen,
as well as for machine
translation systems,
where translation
systems want to output
only sentences that are likely.
So the basic job of a
language model is to input
the sentence which I'm going
to write as a sequence y^1,
y^2 up to y^ty,
and for language model,
it'll be useful to
represent the sentences
as outputs y rather
than as inputs x.
But what a language
model does is it
estimates the probability of
that particular
sequence of words.
How do you build
a language model?
To build such a
model using a RNN,
you will first need a training
set comprising a large corpus of
English text or text from
whatever language you want to
build a language model of.
The word corpus is an NLP
terminology that just means
a large body or a very large
tens of English sentences.
Let's say you get
a sentence in your
training set as follows,
cats average 15 hours
of sleep a day.
The first thing you would do
is tokenize the sentence,
and that means you would form
a vocabulary as we saw
in an earlier video,
and then map each of
these words to say
one-hot vectors or to
indices in your vocabulary.
One thing you might
also want to do
is model when sentences end.
So another common
thing to do is to add
an extra token called
EOS that stands for
end of sentence,
that can help you figure
out when a sentence ends.
We'll talk more
about this later.
But the EOS token can be
appended to the end
of every sentence in
your training set if
you want your model to
explicitly capture
when sentences end.
We won't use the
end-of-sentence token
for the problem exercise
at the end of this week.
But for some applications,
you might want to use this,
and we'll see later where
this comes in handy.
In this example, we have y^1,
y^2, y^3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
Nine inputs in this
example if you
append the end of sentence
token to the end.
Doing the tokenization step,
you can decide whether or not
the period should
be a token as well.
In this example, I'm just
ignoring punctuation,
so I'm just using day
as another token and
omitting the period.
If you want to treat the period
or other punctuation
as the explicit token,
then you could add the period
to your vocabulary as well.
Now, one other detail would be,
what if some of the words in
your training set are
not in your vocabulary?
If your vocabulary
uses 10,000 words,
maybe the 10,000 most
common words in English,
then the term Mau as a decision,
Mau's breed of cat,
that might not be
in one of your top
10,000 tokens.
In that case, you could take
the word Mau and replace
it with a unique
token called UNK,
which stands for unknown words,
and we just model the chance of
the unknown word instead
of the specific word, Mau.
Having carried out the
tokenization step,
which basically means taking
the input sentence
and map here to
the individual tokens or
the individual words
in your vocabulary,
next, let's build an RNN to
model the chance of these
different sequences.
One of the things we'll see on
the next slide is that
you end up setting
the inputs x^t to be
equal to y of t minus 1.
But you'll see that
in a little bit.
Let's go on to build
the RNN model,
and I'm going to continue to use
this sentence as the
running example.
This will be the
RNN architecture.
At time zero,
you're going to end up computing
some activation a_1 as a
function of some input x_1,
and x_1 would just be
set to zero vector.
The previous a_0 by convention,
also set that to vector zeros.
But what a_1 does
is it will make
a Softmax prediction to try to
figure out what is the
probability of the first word y,
so that's going to be y_1.
What this step does is
really it has a Softmax,
so it's trying to
predict what is
the probability of any
word in a dictionary,
what's the chance that
the first word is a,
the first word is Aaron,
and then what's the chance
that the first word is cats,
all the way up to
what's the chance
the first word is Zulu,
or what's the chance that
the first word is
an unknown word,
or what's the chance that
the first words is in
a sentence though or
shouldn't happen really.
Y hat 1 is output
according to a Softmax,
it just predicts
what's the chance that
the first word being
whatever it ends up being.
In our example, one of
the bigger the word cats.
This would be a 10,000
way Softmax output.
If you have 10,000 word
vocabulary or 10,002,
I guess you can't
unknown word and
the sentence has two
additional tokens.
Then the RNN steps forward to
the next step and has
some activation a_2
in the next step.
At this step, it's
job is to try to
figure out what is
the second word.
But now we will also give
it the correct first word.
We'll tell it that G in reality,
the first word was
actually cats,
so that's y_1,
so tell it cats.
This is why y_1 is equal to x_2.
At the second step,
the output is again
predicted by Softmax,
the RNN's job is
to predict what's
the chance of it being
whatever word it is,
is it A or Aaron,
or cats or Zulu,
or unknown word or
EOS or whatever,
given what had come previously.
In this case, I guess
the right answer was
average since the sentence
starts with cats average.
Then you go on to
the next step of
the RNN where you
now compute a_3.
But to predict what is the
third word which is 15,
we can now give it
the first two words.
We're going to tell cats
average of the first two words.
This next input here,
x_3 will be equal to y_2,
so the word average is
input and its job is to
figure out what is the
next word in the sequence.
Another was trying to figure
out what is the probability
of any words in the
dictionary given that
what just came before
was cats average?
In this case, the right
answer is 15 and so on.
Until at the end,
you end up at I guess
time step nine,
you end up feeding
it x_9 which is equal to
y_8 which is the word day.
Then this has a_9 and its
job is to open y hat nine,
and this happens to
be the EOS tokens.
What's the chance
of whatever it is
given everything
that's come before?
Hopefully you'll predict
that there's a high chance
of EOS in the sentence token.
But so, each step in
the RNN will look at
some set of preceding
words such as,
given the first three words,
what is the distribution
over the next word?
This RNN learns to predict
one word at a time going
from left to right.
Next, to train this
through a network,
we're going to define
the cost function.
At a certain time t,
if the true word was yt
and your network Softmax
predicted some y hat t,
then this is the
Softmax loss function
that you'll already
be familiar with,
and then the overall loss
is just the sum over
all time steps of the losses
associated with the
individual predictions.
If you train this RNN on
a large training set,
what it will be able to do is,
given any initial
set of words such as
cats average 15 or cats
average 15 hours of,
it can predict what is the
chance of the next word.
Given a new sentence, say y_1,
y_2, y_3,
with just three words
for simplicity,
the way you can figure
out what is the chance of
this entire sentence
would be, well,
the first Softmax tells you
what's the chance of y_1,
that would be this first output.
Then the second one
can tell you what's
the chance of p
of y_2 given y_1.
Then the third one tells you
what's the chance of y_3
given y_1 and y_2,
and so it's by multiplying out
these three probabilities.
You see much more of
the details of this in
[inaudible] exercise,
it's by multiplying out these
three that you end up with
the probability of this
three words sentence.
That's the basic
structure of how you can
train a language
model using an RNN.
If some of these
ideas still seem a
little bit abstract,
don't worry about it.
You get to practice all of
these ideas in the
coming exercise.
But next it turns out,
one of the most fun
things you can do with
a language model is to sample
sequences from the model.
Let's take a look at
that in the next video.